Register of the Dimitri G. Popescu Papers, 1940-1946
Hoover Institution Archives
Dimitri G. Popescu Papers,
1940-1946
76056
Popescu, Dimitri G., 1908-
6 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoranda, reports, correspondence, and dispatches, relating to Romanian foreign relations during World War II, especially Romanian negotiations with the Allies, and to political conditions in Romania during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Gafencu, G.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Romania.; Romania.; Romania--Foreign relations.; Romania--Politics and government.; Diplomats--Romania.
Container List
- Allied Control Commission, 1946 (Box 1)
- Antonescu, Mihai
  - Correspondence relating to events of August 23, 1944
  - An explanation of the events of 1940 in a letter to L. Giartu, July 30, 1941
  - Personal and political dissensions with Secretary-General Alexander Cretzianu, 1941
  - Secret Contacts in Bern, 1944
- Benes, Eduard
- Bern, secret contacts, 1943-44
- Bessarabia
  - General
  - Romanian Commission for the Application of the Armistice, 1944-45
- Bratianu, G., Neutralite Belge et Neutralite Roumanie (Romanian and Belgian Neutrality), January 1940
- Buzesti, G. N.
- Carol, King, abdication, 1940
- Clippings, 1945-46
- Comintern secret instructions concerning Eastern Europe, 1939
- Daladier, Edouard, Le Proces de Nuremberg et le Pacte Germano-Russe (The Nuremberg Trials and the German-Russian Pact), April 5, 1946
- Europe, Southeastern, political events, 1946
- Events of August 23, 1944
  - The Armistice
  - Armistice negotiations in Moscow
  - Documents, proclamations, reports, 1942-46
  - Documents, proclamations, reports, 1942-46 (Box 2)
  - Negotiations with Soviet military authorities
- Gafencu, Grigore
  - General
  - Interview with Adolf Hitler, April 1939
- Hitler, Adolf
  - Campaign plan for 1939 in case of war, December 1938
  - Intentions for France and other European powers, 1938
- Lisbon, secret contacts, 1943-44
- Madrid, secret contacts, 1943-44
- Pogoneanu, V. I.
- Pop, Valer
- Popovici, Mihai
- Population exchange, 1943
- Romania
  - Eastern boundaries, 1941
  - Ethnic problems along the Northeastern Romanian border, 1943
  - Foreign relations, 1919-1946
  - Internal affairs, 1939-1940, 1943-1944
  - Internal and external problems after joining the Allied Forces in August 1944 (Box 3)
  - Maramures Province
  - Ministry of Foreign Affairs
  - Minority problems, 1941
  - Territorial losses in 1940
- Romania Si Noul Statut Al Balcanilor (Romania and the New Situation in the Balkans), n.d.
- Romanian-German relations, May-June 1940
- Romanian-Russian relations since the 19th century
- Romanian-Soviet armistice, 1944-45
- Romanian-Soviet economic agreements, 1945-46
- Soviet and Ukranian problems, 1940
- Soviet foreign policy, 1933
- Tatarescu, G., Prime Minister
- Ukrainian problem, 1935, 1944
- World War II, German policy toward the Soviet Union, 1940
- Miscellaneous
- Allied Powers negotiations, Ankara, 1944 (Box 4)
- Allied Powers negotiations, Cairo, 1944
- Allied Powers secret negotiations, communications with Romanian Legations in Ankara, Lisbon, and Stockholm, 1943-44
- Romania (Box 5)
  - Ministry of Foreign Affairs-Romanian Legation in Stockholm, correspondence, 1943
- Stockholm, secret negotiations, 1943-44